three amen I want to speak to you today
about a sermon I've entitled the journey
if you had asked me a week ago if I knew
that I was going to preach this sermon
the answer would be no but something
happened to me while I was in Hawaii
which led me to preach this and so let
me tell you the story of the journey so
my wife and I we were in Maui and we my
wife was speaking for the women at the
church the seventh-day Adventist Church
while I was going out kind of like in
the boonies of Maui for the men's
retreat and you know I am uh I consider
myself a very safe person I have a very
good friend named Taj parklet and Todd
likes to do crazy things
hey let's go bungee jumping without a
rope
no Taj I'm not going bungee jumping
without a rope let's let's go swim with
the sharks
no Taj no I'm not swimming with sharks
look at my skin color we don't do that
and so you know I consider myself a safe
person so we were I was there speaking
for the weekend Friday Saturday Sunday
and uh and it's you know just a bunch of
men Y in me I'm there preaching and
stuff and so this one day I'm preaching
and my friend John who had brought us
brought us out there he came with me
said hey pastor listen ah I just
finished speaking and mine the next time
I was gonna speak was at four o'clock so
it was like a two-hour window and I
wanted to like go take an
Knapp you know just kind of rest a while
because that was were still a little bit
jet-lagged from the from the trip over
to Hawaii and so I wanted to take a
little just rest a little bit and kind
of get my mind ready for the message I
was supposed to preach at 4 o'clock at
what time everyone 4 o'clock it is 2
o'clock and I know that I've got to get
prepared for this message before and so
John's like hey listen um we're gonna go
on a little hike and I remember the
words little hike and so you know I
thought to myself well yeah you know I'm
weary I'm tired maybe not you know I
want to stay and prepare and so John was
like no no no come on you got to come on
this height you got to come on this hike
and I'm like yeah he's like we're gonna
go see this waterfall and it's beautiful
and you know everybody jumps in and I'm
like you know I don't do water
especially in Hawaii you know we just
know passable is you don't have to get
in just just just common in other guys
started gathering around and oh pastor
you got to come you got to come and so
you know pride kicks in and pride can be
a dangerous thing you know you know
whole bunch of men around come on be a
man you know and I'm just like yeah all
right
so how long is the site I'm not long you
know half an hour so we'll be back and
so I said all right we'll go I'll come
with you and so off we went on this hike
and I remember you know we we were kind
of a beautiful house you know kind of
out in the country and out so we begin
walking a bunch of us probably about 20s
20 or 25 of us at all when we begin
walking down this trail and we had
walked about maybe 10 minutes or so and
at this point I knew that I did not know
the way back
but I wasn't worried you know cuz we
just going on a hike and so we're
walking past it's like you know kind of
we're on this concrete road and there's
a whole bunch of bushes right and so all
of a sudden I see the people like making
a left turn into the bush and then
they're like come on past and I'm like
what is this and they're like this is
the hike and I'm like that's a bush and
they're like yeah this is how you this
is where we're going so this time I know
that I don't know the way back and I'm
saying to myself I'm really about to
step into these woods and I just want to
show you a little clip here so we're
gonna just play that first click and you
will see could you pause that for a
second please
they actually have me so this is one
minute into the journey go in the middle
of the jungle like hey let's go on a
hike and look at this I'm literally sure
I'm in a jungle
and yeah
see that Jesus swimming with no shoes on
like it's nothing
Wow so that was the beginning and you
know I thought we're in the middle of a
jungle and I don't know they're saying
this is half an hour long so I'm walking
and you know it really begins to kind of
like worry me anybody ever been worried
on the journey so we're going on and
what begins to happen is like we begin
to ascend of this it's it's not even a
path
we're just ascending and I remember at
one point there was a log that we were
up now on a cliff and there's a drop-off
on this cliff that goes right into the
water below and um in my mind I'm
thinking what in the world are they
doing why did they drag me out here
and I'm wondering am I even gonna get
back to even preach at four o'clock so
I'm going to show you another clip let's
just go to that second clip yeah so uh
I'm supposed to speak in
what's on the avocado
I'm recording right now I'm supposed to
speak in like 40 minutes or something
this is were they happening right now
Jerris this raining
and that's where they happened
and they just said you know if I see you
like flashfloods just make sure I run to
the side are you serious are you serious
see that guy right here
I'm not his friend
so that's John and as we're going on
this hike I'm thinking to myself John
I'm gonna put my hands around your neck
have you ever felt like putting your
hands around someone's neck I've ever
felt like putting your hands around any
way so we're going up and this before we
got to this water part we're going up
this this hike and there's this drop-off
and I remember that there was this log
sticking out over the path over the
cliff and the guy in front of me says
okay we have to climb this log
now pride can be a very dangerous thing
because I have guys in front of me and
guys behind me and the guy just climbed
the log and by the way it's wet so it's
muddy and slippery and we're on a cliff
and he climbs along and almost slips so
I'm like in my mind I'm like I'm about
to die but you know outwardly I'm just
like oh it's just a log ok guys what I'm
gonna climb the log and I'm thinking
this can't be happening right now
why did I go on this journey
anyone ever started a journey that
halfway through you wonder why you went
on the journey yeah yeah so so so then
we get down we finally fit what I think
is finishing the hike we get we go all
the way down this this this mountain and
then we get out to this water and that's
a clip you just saw where it's raining
and you have this river just flowing in
rocks so I'm like ok thinking man this
took half an hour well it's time for us
to turn around and go back now and then
they're like no pastor we just got to
the river now we have to go see the
waterfall
and I'm like what do you mean and
they're like yeah the waterfall is about
half a mile upstream and I'm like half a
mile upstream and they're like yeah half
a mile upstream so I said so how are we
going to get there and they were like
well you're gonna take off your sneakers
you're going to put on these shoes that
will help you not to slip as you're
climbing the rocks in the water please
play the next clip
my shoes are gone
my shorts are wet
well
an object lesson I'm learning
the trials of life
can seem very daunting and sometimes
unexpected
yeah when his sillas gonna hike I wasn't
expecting to go on
breathtaking cliffs that you could drop
off road or
go through
this
he ran
so
what you do when the unexpected comes
your way
I guess you take the challenge
they're not that's it
one thing's for sure
I'm not getting back on no forethought
to
my presentation on how to study the
Bible
because I'm gonna be so
and one
and dirty
and falling
does anyone here
it looks like not
another object lesson always ask
questions before you commit to anything
it's not someone tells y'all were just
going to a quick hike you want to ask
how long is quick how do any cliffs
involved are there any other dangers I
should know about because when you don't
ask questions
that's when stuff like
so beautiful
so that's question
so can you be surprised at this last
question don't describe
then there's a powerful lesson though
about forgiveness and you know when
people leads you into stuff this is to
learn how to you know forgive and forget
have you ever started a journey that you
wonder why you started my friends were
so eager for me to see this waterfall
pasture you got to see this you got to
see this and I begin the journey and I'm
just thinking hey quick journey not a
problem it'll be alright I'll be back in
no time for my certain oh no did not
expect to get wet they're not expected
they didn't tell me that there were
mosquitoes on this trail they didn't
tell me that I was going to be soaking
wet by the time they didn't tell me I
was going to be walking through rivers
like for my life they didn't tell me
about flash flood warnings literally
when I got down this this thing and
we're at the river and the guy says to
me by the way if you see the water begin
to rise rapidly just run up the side of
the rock and I'm like but but they had
been on this hike before and it's like
they they knew what they were doing have
you ever started a journey wondered did
I make the right move
I want to take you back to the children
of Israel because up until this week I
have preached about the children of
Israel's murmuring not understanding I
get it now
I get it now because on this whole trip
I was like why do you have me out in
this wilderness to kill me why have you
brought me out here this is a deal what
the murmur I tried I tried and here's
the interesting thing because God God
was eager for the children of Israel to
see something he wanted them to see the
promised land you guys you have to see
this but in order to get there we're
gonna take a little journey we're gonna
go on a hike and you know the story
right you know how Israel begins to to
murmur and how they begin to complain
and how many of them wanted to turn back
have you ever begun a journey in which
you begin to feel like man why did I
start this journey you know we like
things to kind of be a set way you know
I was I had in my mind okay
two o'clock my messages ended and now
I'm going to go take a nap then I'm
gonna get up a small little now I'm
gonna get up and going to prepare my
message for the Lord and then I'm gonna
deliver that message at four o'clock we
like certainty yes I'm used to doing
things this way and so that's the way
that I'm expect that's what I'm
expecting then and God says hey we're
gonna go on a detour it's gonna be fun
trust me I want you to see something I
want you to see this it is so amazing I
want you to see this picture and and
often when we get off on this detour we
don't like it too much do we
we don't like the unexpected we don't
like not being prepared for what's
coming ahead and this is exactly what
the children of Israel go through their
murmuring they're complaining they're
there they think that God has brought
them out in the wilderness to kill them
can journeys be a challenge let me share
with you because many of you do not
realize or maybe you do that God came to
you with some excitement because he
wanted to take you on a want on a
journey you see just like the children
of Israel who were in Egypt anyone know
what the word Egypt
what Egypt symbolized what was a call
it's called the house of what the house
of bondage so God took them on a trip
from the house of bondage to where to
Canaan the promised land a land check
this out
flowing with what milk and honey you got
to see this place that is flowing with
milk I need you to see this picture and
the children of Israel at first were
excited but as they started to walk on
the journey the Bible tells us that they
got discouraged have you ever gotten
discouraged on your journey have you
ever gone through so many cliffs and
almost near-death experiences on your
journey that sometimes you wonder did I
make the right decision and you might
even think about turning around and
going back yet many times I thought
about turning around and going back but
I was like I don't even know the way
back I was now at the mercy of my
leaders I was following this I was
following the Sheep that I was there to
teach
someone said to me out when I got there
like the Shepherd never follows the
Sheep you get in trouble and I was like
yeah but I had to trust those who were
leading me because now I didn't know
where I was going they knew the picture
and I didn't the Bible tells us in
Hebrews chapter 4 verse 1 Hebrews
chapter 4 verse 1
okay Hebrews chapter 4 verse 1 the Bible
says therefore since I promised remains
of entering his rest let us fear lest
any of you should seem to come short of
it we're all on a journey guys every one
of us has begun this journey every one
of us have been walking this journey and
at some point we walked into a jungle
more like ok where am I
and you suddenly realized how helpless
you are because now you are dependent
upon someone else leading you but
beloved you don't have to fear because
that someone else is none other than God
himself
notice with me Galatians chapter 4
verses 3 through 7 Galatians chapter 4
verses 3 through 7 because God calls us
out of the house of bondage and here's
what he says even so when we were
children we were in what bondage under
the elements of the world verse war but
when the fullness of time had come God
sent forth his son born of a woman born
under the law verse 5 to redeem those
who were under the law that we might
receive the adoption as what as sons
verse 6 and because your sons God has
sent forth his spirit the spirit of his
son into your hearts crying out Abba
Father verse 7 therefore you are no
longer a slave but a son and if a son
then an heir of God through Jesus Christ
we were in bondage but God sends us his
spirit and calls us sons now watch this
in the book of Romans chapter 8 verse 14
the Bible says this for as many as are
led by the Spirit of God these are the
wot sons of God saw I want you to catch
this guys God says I am the one leading
you
when you're going through your journey
when you're going through your trials
when you're when you're passing those
cliffs when you're going through those
shrubs when everything looks like man am
I going to find my way in this journey
you need to remember that it is God who
is leading you and if God is leading you
you do not need to be afraid
amen if God is leading you you do not
need to fear
you only need to trust because God has
something that he wants you to see he is
leading you to an amazing waterfall he
is leading you to an amazing River go
with me to the Book of Amos chapter 5
verse 24 this is what he's eager for you
to see Amos chapter 5 verse 24 the Bible
tells us there Amos 5 verse 24 but let
justice run down like what water and
righteousness like a mighty stream gets
where God is trying to lead you to guess
what he wants me to see he wants you to
see the waterfall of righteousness he
wants you to see the waterfall of
justice it is his righteousness and
beloved when we see this waterfall let
me tell you it is worth it it is worth
the journey it is worth the hike it is
worth the rain it is worth the
mosquitoes it is worth the mud it is
worth the the getting wet it is worth
all of that below
so check this out Old Testament Israel
were they a good example were they an
example of how you should travel through
the wilderness no because God was
grieved with many of them therefore they
didn't even make it out of the
wilderness so God says don't be like
Israel I'm gonna show you another
example and you know what he does he
sends us his son and you need to see
this because the Bible tells us in
Matthew chapter 2 verse 14 watch this
Matthew chapter 2 verse 14 Jesus comes
on the scene and Jesus is going to
demonstrate for us how we should travel
through the wilderness how we should
travel on our journey when God is
leading and what he does is he picks up
where Israel failed and he overcomes
where Israel failed
please understand is Matthew chapter 2
Matthew chapter 2 verse 14 the Bible
says when he arose he took the young
child and his mother by night and
departed forward verse 15 and was there
until the death of Herod that it might
be fulfilled which was spoken by the
Lord the prophets saying out of Egypt I
called my son let me ask you a question
what is that what does that mean it
would be fulfilled out of Egypt I called
my son
do you remember in the Old Testament
that when God sent Moses to Pharaoh he
said let my son Israel go remember that
where was he calling his son Israel out
of out of bondage out of Egypt so now
when Jesus comes on the scene God takes
that verse and applies it to his son
that means his son is the new Israel did
you catch that he is the new Israel and
watch what the new Israel does listen
God says look old Israel not a good
example if you follow them you will
murmur on your journey so I'm going to
give you a new example and the new
example will be through Israel my son
otherwise known as Jesus
so God calls his son Israel his son
Jesus out of the wilderness in 1st
Corinthians 10 one and two the Bible
says that when the children of Israel
crossed the Red Sea it was a type of
baptism amen let me ask you was Jesus
baptized just as Israel went through a
baptism did Jesus go through a baptism
yeah and after Israel goes through this
baptism did they go into the wilderness
where the first thing that they cried
out for was bread yes or no what happens
when Jesus crosses the Jordan and then
goes into the wilderness what happens
Satan comes to him and says turn this
stone into one breath I'm answer
question it's Jesus
reliving or is Jesus going through the
history of ancient Israel in his own
person this is very interesting you know
what Israel's second issue was after
they crossed the Jordan after the the
raining down of bread the the very next
chapter Exodus 17 it says that they
cried out for water and and Moses got
mad at them remember that story and then
the Bible says that in Exodus 17 I want
you knows of me Exodus 17 verse aw
verse 2 therefore the people can take
we're gonna read all the way to verse 7
therefore the people contended with
Moses and said give us water that we may
drink so Moses said to them why do you
contend with me why do you want tempt
the Lord let me ask you a question do
you remember when Satan came to Jesus in
the second temptation and says throw
yourself down and God will deliver you
and Jesus reply by what what do you say
you shall not want
tempt the Lord your God okay Israel's
third trial
this is exha 17 and that's this twenty
you got the Ten Commandments and that's
this 25 you have the giving of the
sanctuary and then in Exodus 32 you have
the children of Israel building a golden
calf and doing lots worshiping let me
ask you a question what is jesus's third
temptation in the wilderness worship was
Jesus reliving the history of ancient
Israel but where they failed where they
murmured
are you with me the new Israel shows us
this is how you go through your journey
follow the new Israel because the new
Israel will get you to the promised land
it is interesting that at the end of
Israel's journey you know what they do
right they go up against a city called
Jericho remember how it was six days
that they journeyed around Jericho and
then on the seventh day they blew the
trumpet and shouted and the walls fell
do you realize that Jesus in the last
week of his life did you hear me
beginning in the last week of his life
the Bible picks up the account of every
day of Jesus's life beginning with six
days before he dies on the cross very
interesting the walls of Jericho fought
with the children of Israel ancient
Israel with this six-day period between
them entering Jericho and the fall of
the walls of Jericho and now you have
Jesus the new Israel who's six days
before enters Jerusalem and seven on
that seventh day he is on the cross and
the Bible says he shouts he cries with a
loud voice it is finished
and something happened when he did that
guys the walls fell
come with me to Ephesians chapter 2
Ephesians chapter 2 you need to see this
Ephesians chapter 2 beginning with verse
with verse 13 if he's in chapter 2 verse
13 but now in Christ you who were once a
far off have been brought near by the
blood of Christ that is by the sacrifice
of Christ why for he himself is our
peace who has made both one and has
broken down what what fell at the death
of Jesus the middle wall of what
separation that separated us from who
from God
beloved listen to me when Jesus fulfills
the history of ancient Israel not by
murmuring but by trusting the leading of
his father he set an example for you and
I he set the example that said listen if
you trust in the father he will open up
for you rivers of by the way when Jesus
died was his side opened up was there a
stream
so check this out in his in him
following his father he opened up a
stream for us that when we see it we
will say yes the journey was worth it
beloved listen to me
the trial you are on the journey you are
on it may seem like the worst journey in
the world it may seem like how am I even
gonna get through this but let me tell
you God is leading his church amen
God is leading his people do you know
that even the New Testament church the
Bible says that that the woman
revelation 12 the woman was led into the
wilderness for 1260 years let me ask you
was that wilderness a tough period but
who led her there who led her there God
led her there
the Bible says she was given two wings
of an eagle that she might fly into her
place that is prepared for her in the
wilderness God leads you there beloved
because he ultimately is trying to lead
you to a waterfall
and beloved let me tell you the
waterfall is worth it because that
waterfall flows from the throne of
heaven let me ask you a question
okay can you put those pictures up
please those pictures
there's the waterfall
this is what they were like pastor you
gotta see this
there's the waterfall I look happy now I
wasn't happy before that now I might
take pictures snap another one
ah there's me choking John but it was
worth it but I still have to choke him
sometimes you might feel like choking
your pastor pastor sometimes you might
feel like choking your elders sometimes
you might feel like choking you know
that the people who lead sometimes might
feel like choking the guy that convinced
you to take the walk the journey to
Christ but beloved let me tell you in
the end it is worth it
it is worth it sometimes we're not sure
of the way forward sometimes we're
wondering man is the are we gonna end up
all right
Campbell might be thinking man are we
gonna end up all right but listen to me
if we trust God if we trust God he's
gonna show us a waterfall we're gonna
what that journey through the river is
going to be worth it
Falls and all because ultimately love it
beloved listen to me there is a river
that is flowing from the throne of God
it is spoken about in Revelation chapter
22 verses 1 and 2 and God is so eager
for us to see that River and I never
thought about it like this before but if
the throne of God is high and exalted
and the river is flowing from the throne
of God to me that says this is a
waterfall whoa this is a waterfall I've
always thought of the river it's just
like here's the here's the throne it's
on our level and then there's a water
but what if the throne being high and
lifted up and that what can you in let
me tell you how powerful it was to stand
by that waterfall and this is an earthly
waterfall
but of a God is eager for us to see this
river of life anything to you listen you
might be mad now you might be wondering
now why did I go on this journey but I
want to tell you that the journey will
be worth it the one question that they
all asked me after I got back and let me
tell you the journey back I got a
picture with mud on my face I want the
picture here you go on my facebook face
you will see the mud it felt like I had
been through war and what's funny is
that we all had on these green like my
friend John produces search shirts so
the green shirt you saw John 3:16 we all
the men had on green shirts and it
looked like we were in the military it
felt like we were on a military
expedition and when I came back that's
what I felt like I had been through war
with my military buddies there is
something about trial that causes people
who go through it together to end up
closer than they were before if you can
get through on the other side if you
stay on the journey if you make that
journey together there is something
about trial that ends up bringing people
closer together
whatever god is saying it's worth it
don't turn back I want you to see this
picture don't turn back you've got to
see this waterfall and whatever my
appeal to you like I said I did not plan
to preach a sermon like this but when
God took me away from my plans by the
way we didn't get back till 6 o'clock
and you know what when I got back when
we got back everybody showered down like
alright pastor preach we're ready we're
ready there was a detour in my plans and
God set it up that way Wow God said I
want to show you I want to give you a
real-life object lesson and I praise God
for the detour
I wasn't praising God then trust me I
was questioning God God this guy in
front of me almost fell off the cliff I
actually made a recording for my wife
and kids I was like if I don't come back
I want you to know that I did not this
was not by consent they tricked me
I learned something two weeks ago two
weeks ago it was at Julia's um
shower so we were getting the food and
my Mexican brothers and sisters the
salsa was there and I was like is this
spicy they were like no it's mild and I
was like oh and I took it I took it I
took it
not knowing that mild for a Mexican it
isn't not mild for black men but it was
all about perspective I should have
known this is not mild for me it might
be bad for you but it's not for me when
someone says let's go on a quick hike if
they are Hawaiian have questions
have questions because their hike was
not my well-beloved listen the journey
is different for all of us
and God is simply saying listen whether
you think this is spicy or not whether
you're like this is out of my comfort
zone lord I didn't sign up for this
what's going god says listen trust me
because ultimately I am in charge listen
guys I'm not in charge of this church
you're not in charge of this church God
is in charge of his church and sometimes
you might think the people leading you
have no idea what they're doing cuz I
was sore like you guys are crazy and I
whispered that in the video past my eyes
okay yeah I'm fine
they're crazy I have the video I was
like you are crazy where are you taking
me but Ivan ultimately we got to do this
we have to trust that God is in control
so whatever your journey is right now
wherever you are in your journey on the
cliff on the log down in the riverbed
slipping on rocks trust God have faith
in God
because he will see you through